# John "Jack" Chapel

in john-jack-chapel | ⊕ jackchapel.com | ✓ chapel@usc.edu | ■ +1.404.593.5229

# Summary

I am an applied microeconomist with a decade of experience conducting social science research in academic and public sector settings. I enjoy collaborating with multidisciplinary teams, working on a diverse portfolio of projects, and implementing causal inference research designs to inform program and policy improvements.

Fields of Specialization: Applied Microeconomics, Health, Labor, Public Policy

## EDUCATION

Ph.D., Economics, University of Southern California M.A., Economics, University of Southern California B.S., Economics (with distinction), Tulane University 2019–2024 (expected) 2019–2021 2011–2015

## Professional Experience

## U.S. Department of Labor, Chief Evaluation Office

Summer Fellow June–August 2023

- Led independent research project on chronic disease and older workers' labor force participation.
- Presented results to Office leadership and a broader DOL audience.

# University of Southern California, Schaeffer Center for Health Policy & Economics

Research Assistant for Bryan Tysinger, Director of Health Policy Microsimulation

May 2020–June 2023

- Collaborated with interdisciplinary team to implement dynamic health policy microsimulation models.
- Led the design and analysis for a study projecting future health and economic outcomes and estimating disparities in outcomes between Americans nearing retirement with varying economic status.
- Led the writing and dissemination of the same study, including shepherding the paper through peer review and publishing in *Health Affairs*, multiple presentations at conferences, and giving podcast and press interviews.
- Worked extensively with longitudinal Health and Retirement Study data, interacting with Stata and sensitive datasets through a Linux-based server environment.

#### University of Southern California, Center for Economic & Social Research

Research Assistant for Silvia H. Barcellos, Associate Professor

May 2022–June 2023

- Collaborated with USC faculty on projects related to the cognition and well-being of a longitudinal sample of older Americans during the COVID-19 pandemic; presented results to CESR staff.
- Conducted statistical analyses including logistic regressions, attrition analyses and data imputation using Stata.

## Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Division for Heart Disease and Stroke Prevention

Research Fellow (ORISE), Applied Research and Evaluation Branch

June 2015–June 2019

- As economics lead on the Evaluation Team directing national evaluations of federally funded programs/interventions, designed economic evaluations and oversaw contractors performing economic analyses.
- Created data collection tools, built and managed a database that housed national evaluation data reported by state grantees.
- Worked on the Applied Research and Translation team to conduct systematic reviews, policy evidence assessments, and coauthor the Division's seminal Best Practices Guide.
- Collaborated with the Division's Chief Economist on health economics research published in academic journals.
- Developed economic evaluation training materials and instructed practitioners from state/local governments and other public health organizations during in-person and online training sessions and webinars.

### Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Office on Smoking and Health

Research Fellow (ORISE), Evaluation and Economics teams

June 2015-June 2019

- With the Office's senior economist, conducted literature reviews, content analyses, and creation of cost data collection tools.
- Reviewed supporting evidence for the 2014 update of the major publication Key Outcome Indicators for Evaluation Comprehensive Tobacco Control Programs.

John "Jack" Chapel 1 Updated: October 24, 2023

#### ICF International

Intern, Public Health Division

May-August 2012, 2013

• Conducted initial and follow-up interviews with over 100 suicide prevention professionals to support an evaluation of training and referral networks in a federally funded program.

## SKILLS

Software: Stata, ArcGIS, Matlab, NVivo, Microsoft Office suite (Word, Excel, Powerpoint)

Programming: Stata, Python, LaTex, Linux, SQL

Relevant coursework: Applied Econometrics for Program & Policy Evaluation, Big Data Econometrics, Health

Economics, Empirical Analysis of Economic Development, Urban Economics, Industrial

Organization, Political Economy (audit), Labor Economics (audit)

# Professional Activities

**Teaching:** CDC DHDSP Evaluation Coffee Break Webinars; CDC DHDSP 5-Part Webcast on the Basics

of Economic Evaluation; Polygence Tutoring

Referee Service: Public Health Nutrition, INQUIRY: The Journal of Health Care Organization, Provision, and

Financing

Affiliations: American Society of Health Economists

# Honors & Awards

University of Southern California PhD Academy Scholarship and Research Fund small grant; Dornsife/graduate

school fellowship (2 years)

Centers for Disease Control CDC/ATSDR Honor Award for Excellence in Program or Policy Evaluation

(nominated with coauthors)

Tulane University Cum Laude; Dean's List; annual merit-based scholarship

## REFERENCES

Prof. Jeffrey Weaver Prof. Matthew Kahn

University of Southern California University of Southern California

 $\boxtimes$  jbweaver@usc.edu  $\boxtimes$  kahnme@usc.edu

Prof. Silvia H. Barcellos Prof. Bryan Tysinger

University of Southern California University of Southern California

⊠ sbarcell@usc.edu ⊠ btysinge@usc.edu

### Publications 1 4 1

The remaining pages list publications, presentations, and other works.

## Peer-Reviewed Publications

**Chapel JM**, Tysinger B, Goldman DP, Rowe JW. The Forgotten Middle: Worsening health and economic trends extend to Americans with Modest Resources Nearing Retirement. *Health Affairs*. 2023;42(9):1230-1240.

Shantharam SS, Mahalingam M, Rasool A, Reynolds JA, Bhuiya AR, Satchell TD, **Chapel JM**, Hawkins NA, Jones CD, Jacob V, Hopkins DP. Systematic Review of Patient Characteristics, Intervention Features, and Cost of Self-Measured Blood Pressure Monitoring Interventions with Support. *American Journal of Preventive Medicine*. 2022;62(2):285-298.

- MacLeod KE, Chapel JM, McCurdy M, et al. The Implementation Cost of a Safety-Net Hospital Program Addressing Social Needs in Atlanta. *Health Services Research*. 2021;56(3):474-485.
- Hawkins NA, Bhuiya A, Shantharam S, Chapel JM, et al. A Replicable Approach to Promoting Effective Practices: Translating Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Research. *Journal of Public Health Management and Practice*. 2020;27(2):109-116.
- Zhang D, Ritchey M, Park C, Li J, **Chapel J**, Wang G. Association Between Medicaid Coverage and Income Status on Health Care Use and Costs Among Hypertensive Adults After Enactment of the Affordable Care Act. *American Journal of Hypertension*. 2019;32(10):1030-1038.
- Chapel JM & Wang G. Understanding Cost Data Collection Tools to Improve Economic Evaluations of Health Interventions. Stroke and Vascular Neurology. 2019;4(4).
- Yarnoff B, Khavjou O, Elmi J, Lowe-Beasley K, Bradley C, Amoozegar J, Wachtmeister D, Tzeng J, Chapel JM, Teixeira-Poit S, The Paul Coverdell National Acute Stroke Program Team. Estimating the Costs of Implementing Components of Stroke Systems of Care and Data-Driven Quality Improvement in the Paul Coverdell National Acute Stroke Program. *Preventing Chronic Disease*. 2019;16:190061.
- Chapel JM, Ritchey MD, Zhang D, Wang G. Prevalence and Medical Costs of Chronic Diseases Among Adult Medicaid Beneficiaries. *American Journal of Preventive Medicine*. 2017;53(6 Suppl 2):S143-S154.

# In-Progress and Working Papers

The Social Spillover Effects of Changing Public Program Eligibility: Evidence from Out-of-State Medicaid Expansions (Job Market Paper)

Hidden Hypertension and the Labor Force Participation of Older Americans

How the Great Migration Changed the South (with Yi-Ju Hung)

Diseases of Despair and the Growing Rural-Urban Health Divide Among Older Americans (with Elizabeth Currid-Halkett and Bryan Tysinger)

Does Cognitive Functioning Predict Infectious Disease Risk? Evidence from a Panel of Older Americans Early in the COVID-19 Pandemic (with Sivia Barcellos and Margaret Gatz)

#### Presentations, Media, and Other Publications

### Conferences and Invited Presentations: (\* = coauthor, $\dagger$ = poster)

2023: USC Applied Microeconomics Seminar, ACAP Social Determinants of Health Learning Collaborative, California State University-Long Beach Economics Seminar

2022: Aging Society Research Network Annual Meeting

2021: International Microsimulation Association World Congress (2)

2020: Academy Health Annual Research Meeting\*, Aging Society Research Network Annual Meeting\*

2019: American Public Health Association\*, Annual Conference on the Science of Dissemination and Implementation in Health\*, Society for Applied Anthropology Annual Meeting\*, Society for Prevention Research Annual Meeting†

2018: CDC Evaluation Day

2017: Academy Health Annual Research Meeting<sup>†</sup>, Annual Conference on the Science of Dissemination and

Implementation in Health\*<sup>†</sup>, Art & Science of Health Promotion Conference\*

2016: QCOR\* $^{\dagger}$ 

#### Media:

Podcasts: A Health Podyssey (September 2023)

**Reports:** (\* = coauthored)

- "Economic Evaluation: Intervention Cost Analysis in Public Health" (2018) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.
- "Best Practices for Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Programs: A Guide to Effective Health Care System Interventions and Community Programs Linked to Clinical Services" (2017) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.\*
- "What Could Be Addressed in an Evidence-Informed State Workplace Health Promotion Law?" (2017) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.\*
- "The Shands Jacksonville Patient-Centered Medical Home Diabetes and Hypertension Self-Management Education Model: Program Costs Summary" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.
- "From Policy to Implementation: Collaborative Drug Therapy Management in an Independent Pharmacy" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.
- "Science-in-Brief synopsis of Do State Community Health Worker Laws Align with Best Available Evidence?" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.